Guide to the Ye Old College Inn memorabilia, 1915-ca.1960 MS 526
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Ye Old College Inn memorabilia collection
1915 - ca. 1960
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Ye Old College Inn (Houston, Tex.)
MS 526
4 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection contains memorabilia from the Ye Old College Inn. It consists of photographs, a recipe book and a scrapbook from the Ye Old College Inn. The photographs are those taken of Rice college teams and athletes as early as 1915 and they include baseball, basketball, cross-country, football, and track athletes. The recipe book was put together by Ernie Coker who was one of the owners of the Ye Old College Inn. The scrapbook contains photos and news articles pertaining to Owl athletes and their achievements.
Organizational History
George Martin established a restaurant across from the Rice playing fields in 1918 which originated as a small eatery. It soon became a hangout for Rice University athletes and became known as the Ye Old College Inn by 1921. In 1946, Martin turned the restaurant over to Ernie Coker who added the Varsity Room to it in the early fifties. The Varsity Room served as a banquet hall for meetings, sports banquets, and dances. Photographs of Owl athletes hung on the walls of the Ye Old College Inn until the restaurant closed its doors. The photographs and other memorabilia were then handed over to the Rice Athletic Department.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains memorabilia from the Ye Old College Inn. It consists of photographs, a recipe book and a scrapbook from the Ye Old College Inn. The photographs are those taken of Rice college teams and athletes as early as 1915 and they include baseball, basketball, cross-country, football, and track athletes. The recipe book was put together by Ernie Coker who was one of the owners of the Ye Old College Inn. The scrapbook contains photos and news articles pertaining to Owl athletes and their achievements.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This material was transferred from the Rice Athletic Department in 2008. Menu, children's menu, match book, postcard, newsclips donated by David Bynog, Jan. 2018.
General Note
Portions of this collection are available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/21893" title="Ye Old College Inn memorabilia">https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/21893
Index Terms
Subjects
Business; Sports
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University
- Series I: Photographs, 1915-ca.1960, 37823
  - Baseball Photographs, 1922-1924. Three team posed photographs of the Owl baseball team, 37834 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Basketball Photographs, 1915, 1919?, 1924, and 1953-54. Four team photos and an individual photograph of Owl athlete Tony Bell in uniform, 37833 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cross-Country Team photograph dated 1929, 37832 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Football photographs, 37831 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Photographs that are not dated but estimated as taken in the late 1910's, early 1920's. Candid photos of football games against Southern Methodist University and team practices. Photograph of Tony Bell securing the first touchdown ever made against University of Texas, Oct. 17, 1917. Photograph of Owl athletes on the line practicing: Tony Bell, Fred Boetcher, Hal Heath, Eddie Dyer, Van Brown, Bo Pollard, Giant Duggan, Emmett McFarland, Lee Vilbig, Miller Alexander, and Ed Deprato, 1918. Posed photographs of Frank Gerlach, Eddie Dyer, Tony Bell, Fred Boetcher, Red Tatum, Nepos Harlan, Emmett McFarland, Miller Alexander, Geo Powell, Ed Deprato, and "Heavy" Underwood, circa 1918.
  - Football photographs of individual athletes, 1940s - 1950's, 37830 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes photographs of Gerald Weatherly and "Froggy" Williams, John Crow, Charley Malmberg and Weldon Humble (1946), Kozze Johnson, Bill Howton, Dickie Morgle, Don Rhoden.
  - Football Team Photographs 1915-1918, 37829 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains posed team photographs of Owl football teams. There are two team photographs taken in 1915, three in 1916, three in 1917 and two in 1918.
  - Football Team Photographs, 1921-1923, 37828 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains posed team photographs Owl football teams. There is one team photograph taken in 1921, are two in 1922, and three in 1923.
  - Football Team Photographs, 1924-29, 1950-53, 1957, 37827 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains posed team photographs of Owl football teams. There are two taken in 1924, one photograph of the 1925 Varsity Team, one photograph of the 1926 and 1929 teams, and one of each of the 1950-1954 and 1957 teams.
  - Individual and Group Photographs of coaches and athletes, 37826 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    These include a photograph of Jim Thorpe given to George Martin in 1933, Frank Goss and Preacher Lindsey (date unknown), a group photograph with Jess Neeley and Bill Wallace, the rest of the photographs are of unidentified.
  - Photographs of Rice coaches of football, baseball and track, 37825 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Photographs include group photographs of all the Rice athletic coaches of 1923, football coaches circa 1930's, the Southwest Conference Representatives which includes Jess Neely, and The Rice Institute Athletic Coaching Staff circa 1950's. Individual photographs include those of Coach John Nicholson (date unknown), and Coach Ernie Hjertberg with athlete Fred Stancliff (date unknown). Two photographs of coaches signing the "Coaches Table" of the Ye Old College Inn, circa 1950's. The rest of the photographs are unnamed.
  - Track Team, 37824 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Photographs contain posed team photographs in 1915, 1919, 1922, 1924, 1926, 1929 and not dated. There are also candid photographs of team practices, one photograph of Jack Pollard and Howard Eiser, and a signed photograph of Fred Wolcott.
- Series II: Ernie Coker Recipe Book, 1959, 37821
  - A small book of recipes put together by Ernie Coker from his collection in 1959 to celebrate the 40th anniversary of the Ye Old College Inn, 37822 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series III: Scrapbook, 1921-ca.1960, 37819
  - A large wooden bound scrapbook dated from 1921 containing photographs and news articles of Rice University athletes, coaches, and special events dating through the 1950's, 37820 (Box 3)
  - Menu, children's menu, match book, postcard, newclips, 1950s (Box 3)